Register of the Anna V.S. Mitchell Papers, 1920-1944
Hoover Institution Archives
Anna V.S. Mitchell Papers,
1920-1944
67016
Mitchell, Anna V. S.
6 manuscript boxes, 9 envelopes, 1 oversize album, 4 medals. (3.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings, memorabilia, and photographs, relating to World War I relief work in France, 1915-1920, and relief work with Russian refugees in Istanbul, 1921-1936.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Nansen, Fridtjof, 1861-1930.; Nansen International Office for Refugees.; International relief.; Refugees.; Russians--Turkey.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--France.; France.; Russia.; Turkey.
Biographical Note
1915-16 worked in Paris with French Institution for the Blind at Reuilly
1916-17 served in canteen for Belgians in Calais and for the French at Bar-le-Duc
1917-19 organized and directed Cantine des Deux Drapeaux at Chalon-sur-Marne under the American Red Cross
1919-20 head of Post de Secours in the region of Colonne-sur-la-Lyse Pas de Calais
1921-1936 relief work for Russian refugees in Istanbul
Container List
Original Accession
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1922-1944 (Box 1-4.)
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name of corresponent.
  - Acheson, Barclay 1925, 1927, 1929 (Director, General Overseas Operations, Near East Relief) (Box 1.)
  - Aktiebolaget Stockholms Patenbyra 1924
  - Alaeff, C. 1929-1933
  - Alame, Th. 1935
  - Aleeff, Madame
  - Alianoff, Serafima
  - American Committee on the Evacuation of Russian Youth in Exile 1924
  - American Committee on the Evacuation of Russian Refugees from Turkey 1930
  - American Consul in Constantinople 1924
  - American Hospital of Instanbul 1936
  - Anderson, Mrs.
  - Araxis, Miss 1929-1931
  - Artinoff, E. 1930
  - Ashby, Mrs. Corbett 1935
  - Astor, Lady 1935
  - Baker, Harry T. 1930
  - Barkowsky, Gregoire 1925
  - Battle, George Gordon 1927
  - Bedjitsky, Mr. 1930
  - Beliayeff, Olga 1932
  - Berestneff, Nathalie 1924
  - Bird, Charles S. 1924, 1935
  - Bjorset, B. 1929
  - Bogoroditsky, V. 1932
  - Bouimistrow, W.W. 1924-27 (President, Russian Refugee Relief Society of America, Inc.)
  - Bridge, Dr.
  - Bristol, Admiral 1924
  - Bristol, Mrs. 1922-23, 1925
  - Bullard, Mrs. 1935
  - Burgess, Thomas H. 1924
  - Butler, H.B. 1926, 1928 (Deputy Director, International Labor Office)
  - Caldwell, R.J. 1925-28
  - Charpentier, J.M. 1926
  - Childs, S. Lawford 1924-26 (Chief Delegate, Balkans High Commissariat for Refugees, League of Nations)
  - Christian Century, The 1935
  - Coffey, Dr. 1925
  - Coolidge, Mrs. 1929
  - Couteaux, G. 1930
  - Croker, Mrs. 1929
  - Crowdy, Dame Rachel 1927 (Secretariat, League of Nations)
  - Curran, Henry H. 1923 (Commissioner of Immigration, Ellis Island, N.Y.)
  - Cutting, R. Fulton 1927
  - Day, W.H. 1925 (Controller of Supplies, Near East Relief, Constantinople)
  - Demetrius
  - Draper, Ruth
  - Drummond, Sir Eric 1925, 1930 (Secretary General, League of Nations)
  - Duras, Victor Hugo 1930
  - Emergency Fund for Russian Refugees in Constantinople and the Balkan States 1923
  - Ermoloff, Dm. 1923
  - Euler, A. 1924 1924 (Delegate, Russian Zemstvos Union in Bulgaria)
  - Evans, P.M. 1935
  - Feldman, L.E. 1922-28, 1931 (Delegate, Russian Red Cross in Bulgaria)
  - Ferriere, Mademoiselle 1935
  - Fricero, Madame 1926-27
  - Galuzevski, Rostislav A. 1944 (Box 2.)
  - General Relief Committee, Inc. 1926
  - Golitzinsky, Vera 1929
  - Golovine, Pierre N. 1938
  - Gomella, Mr. 1925
  - Gouraud, General 1935
  - Le Gouverneur, Gouvernement Militaire de Paris 1935
  - Grayson, Admiral Cary T.
  - Grew, Mrs.
  - Grujitsky, Victor 1930
  - Hall, Margaret 1923
  - Haritma, Marietche
  - Hesse, P. 1925
  - Hoover, Herbert Clark 1927
  - Hoppin, Mrs. 1929
  - Howard, Mrs. 1924-25
  - Howard, Sarah G.
  - Huber, Max 1931-33
  - Hughes, Miss 1925
  - Huntington, Elizabeth 1935
  - Ignatieff, Count 1927-28
  - Ilowayskaya, Sophie 1937
  - International Migration Service 1925, 1927, 1929, 1935-36, 1941
  - International Red Cross 1925
  - International Student Service 1928 (World Student Christian Federation)
  - Johnson, J.F. 1927-29 (Assistant High Commissioner for Refugees, League of Nations)
  - Johnson, Major J. 1925-1930, 1934-35 (Chief of Refugee Service, International Labor Office, League of Nations)
  - Joint Foreign Committee of the Jewish Board of Deputies and the Anglo-Jewish Association 1928
  - Kasantzeff, N.A. 1928
  - Ken, W. Clark 1938
  - Keretoff, I. 1924
  - Kookharenko, S. 1930
  - Kousina, Madame
  - Kousik, V. 1928
  - de Lannux, Pierre 1927
  - Lansing, Mrs.
  - Leach, Henry G. 1923
  - League of Nations
    - High Commission for Refugees. Constantinople. 1924
    - International Labor Office. Belgrade. 1925
  - Lemtiaugov, N. 1927, 1929
  - Lichensky, Alex
  - Lindsay, Sir Ronald
  - Loomis, Henry B.
  - Magnusson, Leifur 1927 (Director, International Labor Office)
  - March, Mr. 1927
  - Marinkovitch, Dr. V. 1928 (Minister for Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes)
  - Maximoff, Mr. 1925
  - McCormick, Cyrus H. 1922, 1928-29
  - McGrath, Mr. 1924
  - Mihailoff, M. & T. 1927
  - Minister of Norway 1935
  - Mitchell, Clarence B. 1925, 1929-1930
  - Monin, Anr[UNK]e 1928
  - Moore, Mr. 1927
  - Morgan, Edwin V. 1926
  - Morrison, Dr. C.C. 1935
  - Morrow, Mrs. 1929
  - Nadolsky, Tata
  - Nansen, Dr. Fridtjof 1925, 1927-29 (High Commissioner for Refugees)
  - Nansen International Office for Refugees 1931, 1933, 1936-38
  - National Russian Students Christian Association in the U.S.A. 1924
  - Nebolsine, G.
  - Nolan, Miss 1925
  - Novitsky, George (President, Society of Friends of Russian Culture)
  - Novoye Russkoe Slove 1926
  - Olive, V.S. 1924
  - Ossipoff, Theodore 1930-31
  - Panoff, Mr.
  - Pantuckoff, Oleg I. 1928
  - Parycheff, Serge 1927
  - Payne, Judge J.B. 1922
  - Pelekhine, Natalie 1935
  - Perry, Clara E. 1929
  - Penshkoff, Timothy V. 1930-31
  - Peterson, Martha 1925-26 (Box 3.)
  - Petukhova, Nona 1930
  - Phocassoff, Nathalie 1929
  - Piaskovski, M. 1932
  - Pitenko-Petrowsky, E.
  - Poland, W.B. 1922
  - Popoff, Igor 1930
  - de Postels, Mrs. M. 1926-27
  - Practical Technical Cources in Sofia (Bulgaria) 1923
  - Ravndal, Gabriel B. 1924 (U.S. Consul in Constantinople)
  - Razoumovsky, B. 1930
  - Rijov, Nicolas 1924
  - Ring, Mr. & Mrs. 1924
  - Ringland, Arthur C. 1924
  - Roebling, John A. 1930-37
  - Ruggles, Alma 1922
  - Russian American Information & Service Bureau 1930
  - Russian Red Cross. Belgrade. 1924
  - Russian Red Cross Society in Novisade, Serbia. 1925
  - Russian Refugee Relief Society of America, Inc. 1924-28
  - Schebounine, M. 1934
  - Schlemmer, Raymond
  - Scott, Charles 1922 (Acting Director, Foreign Operations, ARC)
  - Service Social d'Aide aux Emigrants 1931
  - Sheltman, Constance 1925
  - Shishkin, Boris B. 1927-28 (President, Russian Literary Society, Columbia Univ.)
  - Sikorsky Manufacturing Corporation 1927
  - Smernoff, Tatiana (President, Russo-Bulgarian Committee of Ladies in Varna)
  - Smith, Lloyd
  - Soushtchinsky, Marie (Head nurse, Russian Red Cross in Bulgaria)
  - Spelt, Anna 1928
  - Spioung, Arcady 1929
  - Stcherbina, Georges
  - Sterladin, Alex 1925
  - Stokes, Anson Phelps 1922-24, 1926, 1928-30, 1934-35
  - Stokes, Mrs. A.P. 1922, 1930-31
  - Straudman, Mr.
  - Sturgis, Mr. 1924
  - Swift, Mr. 1935
  - Taressenkoff, K. & S.
  - Tcharykow, Vera 1937-38
  - Tetkoff, Theodore
  - Thomas, Albert 1926-28 (Director, International Labor Office)
  - Toler, Mr. 1935
  - Tritchel, Dr. 1922 (Chief Doctor, Russian Red Cross)
  - U.S. Department of Labor
    - General 1930
    - Immigration Service 1930
  - U.S. Protection and Indemnity, Inc. European Branch. 1927.
  - U.S. Secretary of State 1929
  - Le Vali de Constantinople 1925
  - Vickrey, Charles V. 1927
  - Vidovsky, Nicolas 1928
  - Walcott, Frederic 1930 (U.S. Senator)
  - Werner, A. 1933
  - Werner, Professor George 1934
  - Whiting, Mrs. Jasper 1922-23 (Chairman, Emergency Fund for Russian Refugees in Constantinople and the Balkan States) (Box 4.)
  - Wilson, Florence 1925-26
  - Wilson, Hon. Hugh 1935
  - Wiren, Alexis 1929
  - Yanchenko, Basil J. 1927
  - Yerokine, Igor S. 1942
  - Y.M.C.A. International Committee. Practical & Technical Courses in Sofia. 1923
  - Yourieff, S. 1928
  - Youssoupoff, Prince 1925
  - Yurevich, Irene
  - Zabegailoff, I. 1936-38
  - Zomnovsky, P. 1925 (Delegate, Russian Red Cross in Bulgaria)
  - Miscellaneous
- SUBJECT FILE, 1920-1940 (Box 4-5.)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, lists, etc., arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Addresses and names (Box 4.)
  - Agreement of the American Committee with the Nansen Office 1931-35
  - American Central Committee for Russian Relief, Inc. Annual Report 1921-22
  - American Committee, Constantinople. Delegates to High Commission Expense account
  - American Committee for Constantinople Russian Refugees
  - American Cooperative Committee Meeting September 26, 1929
  - American Red Cross. Constantinople Chapter
    - General 1923
    - Monthly Bulletin 1922- #5, 6, 9 1923- #16
  - American Red Cross. South Eastern Base. Supply Dept.
  - American Society for Relief of Russian Exiles, Inc.
    - Fifth report 1935-36
  - Awards, certificates, diplomas, passes, etc.
  - Bebek Orphanage
  - Biographic information on refugees (A-B)
  - Cantine feeding - survival
  - Central Bureau for Relief of the Evangelical Churches of Europe 1935
  - Chirgrin, Leonid
  - Constantinople Chapter
  - Contributions
  - Displaced persons
  - Emergency Fund for Russian Refugees in Constantinople and the Balkan States
  - Finances
  - Kaparulin, Valentin
  - Kouzmin-Karavaeff, Madame
  - Nansen International Office for Refugees
  - "New Constitution of the USSR" 1937 by Vera Micheles Dean
  - Ovtchinnikoff, Monsieur
  - Pietukhova, Nona (Box 5.)
  - "Le Probleme des Derniers Refugees Russes de Constantinople"
  - "The Refugee Problem and the League of Nations" 1938 by Michael Hansen
  - Russian conscripts 1931
  - Russian Ecclesiastical Mission in Palestine
  - Russian Refugee Relief in Constantinople
  - Russian Refugee Relief Society of America, Inc. Boston Committee 1924
  - Russian Refugees
    - General
    - Brazil
    - Bulgaria
    - France
    - Panama
    - Peru
    - Serbia
    - USA
    - Uruguay
  - Russian Relief Society of America, Inc.
  - Tolstoy Foundation, Inc.
  - Union of Russian Zemstvos 1923
  - Union of Russian Zemstovos Institutions in Bulgaria
- MISCELLAENOUS
  - Clippings (Box 5.)
  - Medals
  - Memorabilia
  - Miscellaenous notes, documents, etc.
INCREMENT - January 1975
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1914-1954
  - American Board Mission in the Near East, 1936 (Box 6)
  - Betts, Mary, n.d.
  - Bliss, Mildred, 1940
  - Deletoile, Monsieur, 1919
  - Florance, E. L., n.d.
  - France
    - Ministry of Liberated Regions, 1919
    - Pas-de-Calais, 1919
  - Fry, Miss, 1935
  - Gascouin, General, 1920
  - Gertrude, 1939
  - Guedroitz, O., 1935
  - Hockering, Ernest, 1940
  - Hocking, William Ernest, 1941
  - Hughson, Mary H., 1914
  - Johnson, T. F., 1936
  - Kerr, W. Clark, 1941
  - Lawrence, 1954
  - Morawetz, Mrs. Victor, 1951
  - Nollet, General, 1919
  - Pfaffle, Caroline, n.d.
  - Phillips, Tracy, 1942
  - Royce, Josiah, n.d.
  - Selevine, W., 1933
  - Stephens, S., 1916
  - Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1922
  - Miscellaneous
- SUBJECT FILE, ca. 1919-1954
  - Congratulations, tributes, thank-you's, etc. (Box 6)
  - Farwell, Mildred
  - Lemtiougov, Nicholas
  - Passports
  - Refugees of England, Incorporated, 1940-41
  - Religious poetry and songs
  - Rockefeller Memorial, 1922
  - Russian refugees in Istanbul
  - Tolstoy Foundation
  - Urgent Relief for France, 1939-1941
  - Watson, Forbes, "Serving 10,000 Meals a Day", undated
- MISCELLANEOUS (Box 5-6)
  Clippings, medals, memorabilia, miscellaneous notes, documents, etc.
  - Notes, documents, etc. (Box 6)